Guide to the National Organization for Women, New York City Chapter (NOW-NYC) Records TAM.106
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series VIII: Photographs and Negatives
  - Operation Rescue-Schwartz Clinic, May 6, 1988 (Box 43, Folder 38)
  - Operation Rescue-Queens Clinic, undated (Box 43, Folder 46)
  - Operation Rescue-Queens Clinic, undated (Box 43, Folder 44)
  - ["Operation Rescue-Queens Clinic"-Negatives], undated (Box 43, Folder 45)
  - [People-Individuals] "B" Includes Jennifer Brown and Carol Bellamy, undated (Box 44, Folder 24)
  - [People Individuals-"B"-negatives], undated (Box 44, Folder 25)
  - [People-Individuals] "C" Includes Noreen Connell, Christine Craft, 1986, undated (Box 44, Folder 26)
  - [People-Individuals] "D", 1967, 1980, undated (Box 44, Folder 27)
  - [People-Individuals] "E" Includes Barbara Ehrenreich, undated (Box 44, Folder 28)
  - [People-Individuals] "F" Includes New York Councilwoman M. Friedlander, Muriel Fox, Betty Friedan, 1981, undated (Box 44, Folder 29)
  - [People-Individuals] "G" Includes Judy Goldsmith, undated (Box 44, Folder 30)
  - [People-Individuals] "H" Includes M. Hoffman, undated (Box 44, Folder 31)
  - [People-Individuals] "J", 1989, undated (Box 44, Folder 32)
  - [People-Individuals] "K", 1981 (Box 44, Folder 33)
  - [People-Individuals] "L" Includes Ladies Against Women, Susan Lombard, undated (Box 44, Folder 34)
  - [People-Individuals] "M", 1988, undated (Box 44, Folder 35)
  - [People-Individuals] "N", undated (Box 44, Folder 36)
  - [People-Individuals] "O", undated (Box 44, Folder 37)
  - [People-Individuals] "P", undated (Box 44, Folder 38)
  - [People-Individuals] "Q/R" Includes Sally Ride, 1987, undated (Box 44, Folder 39)
  - [People-Individuals] "S", undated (Box 44, Folder 40)
  - [People-Individuals] "T", undated (Box 44, Folder 41)
  - [People-Individuals] "U", undated (Box 44, Folder 42)
  - [People-Individuals] "V", undated (Box 44, Folder 43)
  - [People-Individuals] "W", 1981, 1988, undated (Box 44, Folder 44)
  - Political Figures/Celebrities, 1981, 1984, 1989, undated (Box 44, Folder 45)
  - Political Figures/Celebrities, undated (Box 44, Folder 46)
  - Press Conference in support of Liz Holtzman on steps of Supreme Court Building, Dec 1987 (Box 43, Folder 14)
  - [Press Conference in support of Liz Holtzman on steps of Supreme Court Building-Negatives], Dec 1987 (Box 43, Folder 15)
  - Pro-Choice Rally Washington D.C., Nov 12, 1989 (Box 43, Folder 17)
  - Rally at Bryant Park, NYC-NY Pro-Choice Coalition, Jan 22, 1986 (Box 43, Folder 10)
  - Rape Prevention Committee: Focus 15 Slide Show, 1974 (Box 34, Folder 16)
  - Rehnquist Rally, Aug 1986 (Box 43, Folder 13)
  - Reproduction and its Control Committee: Pro-Choice March, March 1972, N.Y.C. [Includes baby Sleeping in Stroller with Pin, "I'm Not Going to Give Up My Right to Choose"] [35 mm negative] (Box 34, Folder 17)
  - Reproduction and its Control Committee: Abortion Picket Line, June 14, 1974 [Contact Sheet] (Box 34, Folder 18)
  - Reproductive Rights Committee: St. Patrick's Cathedral Demonstration [Contact Sheet Carin Drescher-Marx], 1976 (Box 34, Folder 19)
  - Reproductive Rights Committee: Abortion Teach-In [Photographs by Jean Wertheim], Jan 21, 1978 (Box 34, Folder 20)
  - Reproductive Rights Committee: Demonstration, April 1979 [Color Slides by Linda Grishman] (Box 34, Folder 21)
  - Reproductive Rights Committee: Staten Island Demonstration [Contact Sheets, Negatives; Credit Unknown], 1981 (Box 34, Folder 22)
  - Reproductive Rights Committee: 9th anniversary of Roe v. Wade [Credit Unknown], Jan 22, 1982 (Box 34, Folder 23)
  - Reproductive Rights Committee: 9th anniversary of Roe v. Wade [Photographs by Tom Beckett], Jan 22, 1982 (Box 34, Folder 24)
  - Reproductive Rights March Fifth Avenue, Cherry Hill Demonstration, St. Partrick's Demonstration, undated (Box 43, Folder 34)
  - [Reproductive Rights March-Negatives], undated (Box 43, Folder 35)
  - Slides: 2nd Select Action, Ganley River, undated (Box 40)
  - Slides: Mary Kay, Rosie the Riveter, May 1981 - Jun 1981 (Box 40)
  - Slides: NOW Rally, Jul 1981 (Box 40)
  - Slides: NOW Rally, Jul 1981 (Box 40)
  - Slides: NOW SF, Aug 1982 (Box 40)
  - Slides: NOW Labor Day, 1983 (Box 40)
  - Slides: NOW, undated (Box 40)
  - Slides: NOW Cherry Hill N.U., undated (Box 40)
  - Slides: NOW Copies, undated (Box 40)
  - Slides: NOW Labor Day, undated (Box 40)
  - Slides: NOW PSA, undated (Box 40)
  - Slides: NOW Womens Power PAC, undated (Box 40)
  - Slides: NOW Election Campaign Meeting, undated (Box 40)
  - Slides: NOW Member Meeting, undated (Box 40)
  - Slides: Slides found loose in box, undated (Box 40)
  - Slides: Unidentified shoots, #1-10, undated (Box 40)
  - Slides: Reproductive Rights March, 1981 (Box 40)
  - Slides: Reproductive Rights Coalition March, 1981 (Box 40)
  - Street Fair, 1988, 1989 (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - 16 mm: NOW Wash., Jun 29, 1982 (Box 40)
  - 16 mm: Approach, undated (Box 40)
  - 16 mm: Crowd, undated (Box 40)
  - Unidentified photograph [Johnny Cash and Unidentified Woman], undated (Box 34, Folder 25)
  - [Unspecified events-dated], 1979-1992 (Box 44, Folder 16)
  - [Unspecified events-undated] (Box 44, Folder 17-21)
  - [Unspecified events-undated-negatives with prints] (Box 44, Folder 22)
  - Woman Dead from Illegal Abortion [Graphic], undated (Box Shared Tamiment OS009, Folder 1)
  - [Woman holding "Never Again" sign, photographer Dianna Wade, oversized], 1974 (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - "Woman Power is Too Good to Waste" [Photographs by Marilyn Schwartz], undated (Box 34, Folder 26)
  - "Women March for Equality," August 26, 1971 [Contact Sheets, Bettye Lane Photographer] (Box 34, Folder 27)
  - Women Photographer's NOW Opening, Jun 1986 (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - Women's Equality Day, undated (Box 44, Folder 14)
  - "Women's Equality Day," August 26, 1977, Aug 26, 1977 (Box 34, Folder 28)
  - Women's Equality Day August 27, 1984, Voter Registration Drive, Truth Square Anti-Reagan Demonstration, Pay Equity, Aug 27, 1984, undated (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - Women's Equality Day Rally NYPL, Aug 26, 1982 (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - Women's Truth Squad, 1984 (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - "Witness Women's Lives"-Pro-choice Demonstration at Saint Patrick's, Jun 1985 (Box 43, Folder 8)
  - ["Witness Women's Lives-Pro-Choice Demonstration at Saint Patrick's], Jun 1985 (Box 43, Folder 9)
- Series IX: Artifacts, Ephemera, Graphics and Other Material
  Series includes NOW-NYC artifacts, ephemera, graphics and publicity materials from circa 1970s-1980s. Artifacts and ephemera include a blue and yellow "Partnership in Marriage" felt banner, baloons with NOW-NYC slogans, 3 cross-stitch patterns with "Liberte, Egalite, Sororite", bumper stickers, sheet music for "Liberation Now!", flyers, stickers and programs.
  - 1 Banner: "PARTNERSHIP IN MARRIAGE", undated (Box 108, Folder 3)
  - 7 Balloons: "Ratify the ERA," "A Day for Women's Rights--Ratify the ERA 8/22/77," "I Love Equality / NOW-NYC / Boycott States that Have not Ratified the ERA", 1977 (Box 108, Folder 1)
  - 3 Cross-stitch Patterns: "Liberte, Egalite, Sororite", undated (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - 2 pieces of Lace, [1977-1979] (Box 108, Folder 2)
  - Name tag: "Focus 15: Yolanda Bako", [1975] (Box 108, Folder 1)
  - Arts Committee-Flyers, Programs, 1972, 1974 (Box 107, Folder 1, Box Shared Tamiment 194, Folder 3)
  - Campaign Ephemera, 1990-2016 (Box 105, Folder 10-11)
  - E.R.A. Committee -- Card, Bumper Sticker, 1977-1982 (Box 107, Folder 4)
  - "Liberation, NOW!" Song--sheet music, 1970 (Box 107, Folder 5)
  - Reproductive Rights Committee Bumper Stickers, "STOP Violence Against Women" Stickers, [1977-1979] (Box 107, Folder 3)
  - Clippings (Box 34, Folder 31)
  - Ephemera, undated (Box 34, Folder 30)
  - Graphics, undated (Box 34, Folder 31)
  - Various NOW Documents [Includes Press Releases; "National Organization for Women: Woman Power Project" Report on Referral System; NOW-NYC Training Manual; "NOW-NYC A Case Study"; Workshop Materials, circa 1977-1995 (Box 34, Folder 32)
  - Proclamations of Women's Equality Day (2) and ERA Countdown Day (1) from the Mayor of New York State, 1981, 1982 (Box Shared Tamiment 194, Folder 6)
  - 3 NOW Transparencies, undated (Box 37, Folder 8)
  - Layouts for NOW Handouts, 1991, undated (Box 107, Folder 2)
  - Proclamation from Governor of New York State for Susan B. Anthony Day (3), Women's Equality Week, Women's Equality Day, ERA Countdown Day, International Women's Day, and Resolution, 1978-1984 (Box Shared Tamiment 194, Folder 5)
  - 1 Hat "Carol Bellamy Election Day Team and 1 visor "NOW/PAC Woman" (Box 108)
  - 33 Miscellaneous Buttons, undated (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - 4 Boxes -- Film Strips and Film Containers -- "Women Now Pt. 1" (2) and "Women Now Pt. 2" (2) by Feminist Productions Inc. Babylon, NY, undated (Box 108)
  - 2 "ERA YES" Stamps and 1 Prescription Bottle with Label "FOR EQUALITY", undated (Box 108)
  - 3 T-shirts "We'll Remember Each November ERA YES" "Keep Your Laws Off My Body" and "Pro Choice NOW", undated (Box 37, Folder 3-5)
  - NOW-NYC Totebag, undated (Box 94)
  - Four ERA T-Shirts, 1981-1982 (Box 94)
  - Pink kerchief, undated (Box 94)
  - The NOW York Times, The Trulytzer Prize, Women's Equality Day Proclamation, 1971-1981 (Box Shared Tamiment OS009)
  - ERA Banner (Box Shared Tamiment 023)
  - "ERA-YES" Banner, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 194, Folder 4)
  - 'Tis the Season to be Equal Poster, circa December 1971 (Flat-file-folder TBD)
    Scope and Contents
    Large scale drawing of holiday poster or card depicting a townhouse facade with Shirley Chisholm for President sticker affixed to top left corner.
  - Equal Rights Divorce Reform Bill Banner (Flat-file-folder 1)
    Homemade banner made by members of the NOW Marriage and Divorce Committee, likely of the New York City Chapter, measuring 51.5 inches by 24 inches.
- Series X: "Our North American Foremothers" Documentary
  Materials from NOW's circa 1972 multimedia documentary, "Our North American Foremothers", written and produced by Anne Grant. Includes over twelve hundred slides depicting historical figures (primarily portraits), places, documents, and artifacts from the struggle for women's rights, a twenty-five page script for the show narrating the history of women's rights and feminism, photographs, and ephemera. Also includes four reels of 16 mm film made for the project by Maria Lessing but not included in the final project.
  Note: the script is also located in Series V: Programs, and correspondence about copyright is located in Series II: Correspondence.
  - NOW Slides, Vol. 1: 1-14 [1 of 2], undated (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - NOW Slides, Vol. 1: 1-14 [2 of 2], undated (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - NOW Slides, Vol. 2: 15-30 [1 of 2], undated (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - NOW Slides, Vol. 2: 15-30 [2 of 2], undated (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - NOW Slides, Vol. 3: 31-44 [1 of 2], undated (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - NOW Slides, Vol. 3: 31-44 [2 of 2]
  - NOW Slides, Vol. 4: 45-60 [1 of 3], undated (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - NOW Slides, Vol. 4: 45-60 [2 of 3], undated (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - NOW Slides, Vol. 4: 45-60 [3 of 3], undated (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Script, Cards, Photographs (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Unidentified Portrait, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 9)
  - Slideshow Opening Credits [Color Photographs], 1972 (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - "Loretta", [1974]; cuid34962 (Box 38, Reel cuid34962, Box 44, Folder 49)
    The paper materials include one letter describing the production of the film by Maria Lassnig for the Foremothers Project.
  - "7252 / Lassing / Harriet Tubman" [small reel (50 ft.)], [1974]; cuid34963 (Box 38, Reel data_value_missing_c4fb7a6bc318db9a41c678c113082284)
  - "7256 / Lessing" [small reel (50 ft.)], [1974]; cuid34964 (Box 38, Reel data_value_missing_155435eebe56b706720e9773a3fc6c98)
  - "Loretta and Claudia on the bycycle [sic]" [Small Reel (50 ft.)], [1974]; cuid34965 (Box 38, Reel data_value_missing_ca46ec92370841237d9a0b9e89066491)
  - "Lessing / first close-ups / Mon / Loretta on the bycicle [sic]" [small reel (50 ft.)], [1974]; cuid34966 (Box 38, Reel data_value_missing_b867dd9d48d212fe6c06c1c305271eba)
  - List of Historical Women, circa 1970-1984 (Box 36, Folder 7)
- Series XI: Radio Recordings, Symposiums and Conferences
  Includes audio cassettes, reel to reel tapes, and film from conferences and radio and television programs from the mid-1970s. Audio cassettes and reel-to-reel tapes of radio recordings and symposiums/conferences.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Some recordings in this series are missing as of October 2019, and are therefore not available to researchers.
  - NOW Meeting #1 [1/2" open reel video tape], Mar 22, 1973 (Box 38)
  - NOW Meeting #3 [1/2" open reel video tape], Mar 22, 1973 (Box 38)
- Series XII: Audiovisual Materials, circa 1984 - 1990
  - Legal Abortion But For Whom, Moderated by Jennifer Brown, January 1, 1985; cuid34465 (Box 41)
  - Divorce, New York Style, November 27, 1984; cuid34466 (Box 41)
  - Reproductive Rights, April, 1984; cuid34467 (Box 41)
  - When Children are Battleground, Moderated by Jennifer Brown, January 14, 1986; cuid34468 (Box 41, U-matic cuid34468)
  - Women's Health Issues, Moderated by Jennifer Brown, March 3, 1986; cuid34469 (Box 41, U-matic cuid34469)
  - Feminization of Poverty, Moderated by Jennifer Brown, May 28, 1985; cuid34470 (Box 41, U-matic cuid34470)
  - Educating Women: With or Without Men, April 9, 1985; cuid34471 (Box 41, U-matic cuid32271)
  - Closing the Wage Gap, October 22, 1985; cuid34472 (Box 41, U-matic cuid34472)
  - Seven open reels, mostly NOW PSAs. Labels include "Voter Registration" and "Women and Economic Justice.", circa 1984-1990 (Box 42)
- Series XIII: Legal Cases, 1994-2001; 1 Linear Feet
  This series contains legal briefs primarily relate to the cases NOW v. Pataki and NOW v. Cuomo in which the organization served as a third-party representative for plaintiffs aginst the New York State Human Rights Division. The plaintiffs claimed that the Human Rights Division violated their right to due process by delaying or failing to properly address legal complaints of workplace sexual harassment. Briefs include plaintiff declarations, memoranda, affirmations, testimony, and appeal petitions dated 1997-2001. The series also includes several other legal briefs from 1998 related to cases of workplace sexual discrimination.
  - Division of Human Rights Lawsuit: National Organization for Women v. Pataki, 1994-2001 (Box 45)
  - Division of Human Rights Lawsuit: National Organization for Women v. Cuomo, 1997-1998 (Box 45)
  - Rosario v. National Bank of Pakistan, 1998 (Box 45)
  - Martens v. Smith Barney Inc., 1998 (Box 45)
- Series XV: Archived Website, October 2007-ongoing; 2 websites in 2 archived website.
  The New York City chapter was the founding chapter of the National Organization for Women. Their website includes information on the latest news and events regarding NOW-NYC, Women of Power and Influence awards, their priorities, and ways to get involved. NOW's priorities include reproductive rights, constitutional equality, LGBTQIA+ rights, promoting diversity, violence against women, and economic and social justice. Crawling of their website began in 2007, and focused on misogyny in media and the Supreme Court decisions to uphold the Federal Abortion Ban. In 2008, a more complete capture of the website was taken and included issues of their newsletter, whatNOW (dating back to 2005); action campaigns related to New York's Reproductive Health Act, the Clinic Access Bill, the Freedom of Choice Act, sex-trafficking, and emergency contraception prices; their political action committee and endorsements; photo galleries from protests; and their Service Fund and legal clinics which provides legal assistance and other support regarding discrimination, domestic violence, and other issues. In 2009-2013, the website contained efforts to support marriage equality, midwifery reform, Anti-Strangulation Bill, divorce reform legislation, subsidized child care, sexual violence programs, the publication of sex crime statistics, Disclosure Law for pregnancy service centers, insurance coverage of contraception, equal pay, discriminatory advertising practices, Reasonable Accomodations for Pregnant Workers Bill, Violence Against Women Act, and funding for Planned Parenthood. In September 2010, they launched the Take Rape Seriously Campaign. The website also included report cards on how politicians voted on bills supported by NOW-NYC.
  In 2013, the website redesigned and promoted action campaigns related to the Women's Equality Act, ending sexual harassment in all workplaces, pay equity, pregnancy discrimination, protecting abortion clinics, birth control access, and fighting human trafficking. In 2014-2017, campaigns included sexual assault in the military, the women's equality agenda, expansion of family court judges, the Burwell v. Hobby Lobby Stores Supreme Court case, untested rape kits, funding for sex-trafficking victims, holding NFL players accountable for domestic abuse shackling of incarcerated women during childbirth, consent education to schools, the Helms Amendment, ending child marriage, holding police accountable for violence, campaigns against President Trump's cabinet selections, stopping anti-choice legislation, immigration and rufugee ban, and birth control access. In 2018, NOW worked to against Trump presidency agenda, such as preventing Brett Kavanaugh from being confirmed to the Supreme Court (which was unsuccessful) and get out the vote efforts.
  In 2019, the website redesigned to its most recent iteration (as of this writing). Action campaign categories focused on by NOW-NYC include resisting President Trump's agenda, New York City elections, reproductive healthcare, reproductive justice, equality and justice, changing laws, and workplace rights. Campaigns through 2022 included holding the NYPD accountable to survivors of sexual assault, madating sexual education for public school students, ending gun violence, ending abusive practices for home healthcare workers, closing the NY State Intoxication Loophole, and protecting abortion.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
  Accruals
  New site crawls are accrued semiannually.